as this crisis unfolds we've really
started looking at different ways we can
start and try to make sense of it we've
looked at complexity and now in this
film we're looking at mythopoetic s--
and this is a subject really close to my
heart because I'm a writer and I've
always been fascinated by myth and the
idea that myth can teach us something
about being human and how to be in the
world that we can't really get from
anywhere else so I'm fascinated by
looking at myth is almost like a kind of
hidden code in the stories we tell this
is one of the really interesting things
about looking at things through a mythic
lens is that stories and structures of
stories repeat over and over again and
right now when we're in a crisis like
this and everything is uncertain myth is
really coming into its own as a way to
start to make sense so I spoke to three
people whose work I really admire in
this area and they were Zach Stein who
is a psychologist and also an education
reformer and he wrote this brilliant
piece recently called
a war in heaven were on a very intense
journey yeah worth a couple lifetimes
like it's very intense but I think at
this point it's it's less like we've got
a map and we know where we're going and
more like again to use another image of
from biblical myth it's like wandering
in the wilderness together this is where
we are I wanted to speak to someone who
is an expert on on death and dying and
our cultural attitudes towards that and
I couldn't think of anyone better than
Stephen Jenkinson who is I used to be a
palliative care counselor and worked in
a large hospital in North America and
was with thousands and thousands of
people as they died so Stephen Jenkinson
has written a lot about how a person can
die well and I was curious to ask him
about how does a culture die well again
I learned this thing at the district so
you really love somebody who's dying yes
do you think they're dying
do they refuse to be dying or are they
dying because the answer to that
question determines what you do next so
let's say they're dying they don't agree
that they are but they are they're in
the early stages of it
what is the etiquette of your
relationship with them how do you
conduct yourself as if what's happening
is happening that becomes the question
for a dying person in your household and
it becomes the same question for a time
like now where we get to glimpse how
utterly exhausted our acquisitive way of
doing things has become so I also spoke
to Charlotte akan and Charlotte is a
writer and a storyteller she's one of
the editors of the dark mountain project
which is a publication that like rebel
wisdom explores systemic fragility and
explores the kind of mythopoetic
substructure of of culture as well you
know you can live up here with it as a
story and it isn't lived but I think we
are being absolutely I don't think
that's how they were written and I don't
think that's what we need to do it I
think we need to embody so this is
something we've been looking at since
the beginning of the channel like what
are the deep stories of culture trying
to tell us from Jordan Pederson looking
at kind of the deep source code of the
Bible and pre-biblical
knowledge to I think the the best that I
heard was Jordan Hall summarized it in
one of our interviews where he talks
about the mythopoetic layer being the
place where we put knowledge that we
might only need once a generation or
once a millennium this is the thing that
Jordan Peterson is I think most clearly
trying to articulate in their space you
know our archetypes our mythologies the
ones that cover a lot of cultures and
lasts a long time do so because they are
the things that have been most deeply
associated with what is worked
those cultures that do certain things in
certain ways endure and we perceive them
as stories so we can we can listen to
them but it's not the stories that
matters the embodied practices if you're
not living it you're not doing the
religious aspect where would you store
that information or you'd store it in
the deep in the deep mythopoetic layer
and the stories that underpin the
culture so
this really feels like a time where we
should be going into that deeper
mythopoetic layer and pulling out what
what has been stored there by our
ancestors for the times that we're going
through now there are also a few themes
that really came out as I was talking to
people and so the first one is this idea
of the liminal the liminal means that
space between and Zach Stein he calls it
that that space between worlds which i
think is a really nice way to talk about
it and the liminal is a weird place in
myth because we step past some kind of
threshold that's interesting that we're
at threshold actually comes from the
from doorway that's the doorway and we
have actually done that as specie if
we've stepped through our doorways into
a place that's very familiar to us our
homes but in this insanely unfamiliar
situation so you step past the threshold
and then you're in this world that is
sort of between things you know in in
stranger things that's the upside down
right it's kind of like our world but
it's all inverted the rules that used to
apply didn't apply and Zach Stein really
spoke of this really beautifully so it's
gonna play a clip of where he goes into
it in a bit more detail what's your
what's your sense on what that space
means psychologically or mythically like
what what does it really mean to be
right now in a space between worlds
right I mean it's it's disorienting
that's the first thing it's a storage
again scary and this is like when you
wouldn't remember I said like once you
reach a certain age it becomes hard to
die to yourself and create it yourself
one of the main reasons for that is
because of the disorientation and fear
that sets in when one world is no longer
the world and another world hasn't set
in and you know so the experience is one
of being on unmoored and seeking for
some deeper root than the superficial
things that were grounding you and so it
is both a feeling of disorientation and
a feeling of grasping one
or imagining right and and so that's the
place where though kind of metaphor of
the war of Heaven comes in because it's
in that opening of imagination where
there's this battle between the
different kind of voices and archetypes
that populate the human psyche but when
the world's just running heaven stays
put right and there's a fan of season we
watched them on TV about what's gonna
happen like but when the world starts to
shift and change radically
then you heaven and earth kind of
collide and in your own imagination you
start to see possibilities in the actual
world that look hellish or heaven like
right and this is what we're saying is
that everyone's imagination is going to
the possibility of worst-case these
terrible things that you who wish
thought you'd only ever see on a movie
now all of a sudden are like flooding
into your actual experience things that
were mythic in the sense of being like a
myth that you watch on the screen are
now like playing out in front of you
right so there's this the heaven and
earth collide and similarly other people
are saying this the possibility for a
radical positivity to come out of this
on the other end right then out of the
moment in response to tragedy and pain
when utopia could be forged right and so
again like heaven this fantasy of a
completely different economic system
like this fantasy which would stop the
capitalist world system with a button
and every one thing grinds to a halt
wait a second that just happened right
so it's like heaven and earth collide
again and there's this incredible
imaginal potency which makes the choice
the feeling of choice dizzying because
it's like you know are you gonna turn
into a bad guy or you're gonna turn into
a hero right usually you don't even have
to ask that question because you're just
afraid you as a guy but now depending
what happens would the way this plays
out you may have to choose between
in being a villain being a hero right
acting how to complete selfishness to
protect yourself or giving of yourself
to help others right yo there will be
the opportunity to make real choices
that affect character and and so that's
the other thing that happens between
worlds is that I think there's a line in
the paper I say you know precious are
the moments of world making and this is
the case in your own life when you know
you're in between and you're at those
critical choice points right when
relationships end when jobs and people
die when health crises hits you know
that in those moments the choices you
make are more pronounced because you're
at the beginning of a new fork in the
road yes of the time between worlds also
feels ethically charged feels like the
moments are more important what do you
do with your time matters more and so I
was speaking to Vega yesterday and we
were just where's the day before and we
were going on this notion of Kairos
right that it's this potency time this
pregnant time the time between worlds
which again is not a good - it's not
like happy time it's not like yay you
know it's not at all like that it's
actually quite scary and terrifying
um but also again part of that part of
human experience so we are experiencing
something that although it's nominal
humans experience this like this is what
humans have since we've been humans
experienced the sense of the whole
system we're all in it together and the
whole system something's happening right
like again the flood myth like that's
what that story's about
it's like oh my god a flood is coming
like we used to be not friends and like
battling and like there's all this stuff
happening before this but now this is
happening and just overwhelming
collective kind of opening of the psyche
towards fear towards love right the way
more energy and
kind of like dynamics in the mind and in
the culture so yeah that that's what it
feels like a little bit to be Minotaur
between worlds for those who would see
this this crisis as terrible as it is as
simultaneously a call to adventure where
that adventure might be towards maybe
every individuals will be different but
do you think without obviously asking
you to map out the future well is there
some kind of a tractor that you feel we
might be moving towards as we as we move
forward
interesting the adventure is not that
were I don't think adventures the word
that I use that I wouldn't use the word
adventure it's it's not an adventure
it's more like a potentially ecstatic
ordeal right that it's a potentially
beautiful tragedy or redemptive tragedy
um but you know there's a crucifixion
before the resurrection and hurts so the
kind of journey that were on is the
journey that we have sketched out a
little bit he writes this journey into
death
it's a journey into depth and into
intimacy and relationship unnecessarily
physical close proximity although you
will be perhaps locked in a house with
people for a while but a deepening of
intimacy because you know every phone
call you have could go there you know
what I mean it's like it's gonna be hard
to keep pretense of normalcy Emma that
means that we're all open to the depths
of one another so we're on an adventure
in - yeah it's like a for a fear of
sounding cheesy and like a soul
adventure it's it's uh it's uh it's a
journey of deepening in Solman of
individual and species and you know when
you think of that notion of in Solman
it's a term I use technically and that's
another conversation but tragedy is the
structure of insulting a pain right
depth and the grappling and the
employment with others rather than
separation with others so yeah in that
sense the immediacy of it's it's a side
we're on a we're on a very intense
journey yeah it's worth a couple
lifetimes like it's very intense and
then there will be changes physically
like to commodities supply change to
economics and so there will be a a
social economic journey basically but I
think at this point it's it's less like
we've got a map and we know where we're
going and more like again to use another
image of from biblical myth it's like
wandering in the wilderness together
this is where we are and so when you're
in the wilderness you have to bring your
temple with you right it becomes not a
temple in space but a temple in time and
it allows you even though you don't know
exactly where you're going to be
together um all right in that shared
container of meaning and so in that
sense yeah we're on that pilgrimage our
wandering through the wilderness and so
I'm arguing not arguing I'm basically
pleading for is that we remember to
create these temples in time where we
can be together in reality no matter how
bad it gets and know that it this is
what humans have always done in a sense
it's kind of like what we're made for is
to experience the intense and tragic
beauty of life together and yeah so
that's a little bit of that so
yeah not an action-adventure movie not
at all
so another theme that really emerged
talking to everybody was this theme of
death and rebirth so that as we go
through a transition something it
necessarily has to die you know a lot of
people are talking about that the system
that we've been in has to die for
something else to come out of it
my sense is after 65 harrowing years in
the planet that people rarely do their
best sorry to say it out loud but there
it is
if this is our best you know what we've
done to the thing entrusted to us God
Almighty
either we're not doing our best or god
help us this is our best I'm going with
I think the more humanly benevolent
vision that we're not doing our best
that's the first thing and so we can't
fall back on the idea that left to our
own devices will get it straight we are
being left to our own devices and we're
not getting it straight you see so we're
going to have to be defeated
my vision vision scuse me is the sooner
we're defeated the better for all
concerned do I know what that looks like
am I not aware that there's all kinds of
wreckage of various kinds that are that
will ensue from what I'm saying yeah man
I don't have the blueprint right but if
you're asking me as a citizen of a
troubled time then my responsibility as
a citizen is to glimpse the end or the
extinction of this particular kind of
citizenship you know our regime has no
business being in the world this is a
demonstrable fact it's not an opinion
it's a fact even though the likes of and
I really adore Jordan Peterson but when
he continued in the old days it seemed
so long ago now to favor the the
developments of the West and so on I
think I understand why he would do so
but he has to ignore certain other
things at his peril in order to make
that case sadly so again I learned this
thing at the death trade so you really
love somebody who's dying yes do you
think they're dying
do they refuse to be dying or are they
dying because the answer to that
question determines what you do next so
let's say they're dying they don't agree
that they are but they are they're in
the early stages of it
what is the etiquette of your
relationship with them how do you
conduct yourself as if what's happening
is happening that becomes the question
for a dying person in your household and
it becomes the same question for a time
like now where we get to glimpse how
utterly exhausted our acquisitive way of
doing things
has become so what do you do an answer
to my mind is you bear faithful witness
to the the realities of the dying and
you you orchestrate yourself in the
presence of the dying not to spite it
not to overcome it not to pretend it's
not there for the sake of mutual comfort
but to risk it all to risk the
relationship to friendship whatever it
is and and failure and fail to conspire
with the idea that there's more time
there isn't more time and that confers
this upon this time a real sense of
urgency and if I really love you
I'm gonna be be with you as if you won't
be around much longer right and it how
that makes you feel in the short term
well it's gonna be wild and and and
strange and we don't know how to do it
we don't have an etiquette for endings
in a culture that doesn't believe in
them so it's one of the reasons I guess
I ended up doing that book is to try to
advocate for a sense of you could say
fundamental etiquette our existential
etiquette an etiquette of kind of
radical love about what it means to see
something down that's the phrase I came
to use to describe it and that's what we
have to do now we have to be willing to
see our regime down of course
it means living with a lot less
including a lot less certainty and no
sense of safety I mean my country
embarrasses me as they as they whine and
mule at the government for the you know
the the sustaining handout instead of
the death look man the situation was
completely anticipated it's
unprecedented but it's completely
anticipated okay now you've had a taste
how many more taste you want don't make
a meal of this push away from the table
now and something else that usually
comes out through through very old myths
is that they teach us something about
our role as human beings in the world
and Steven Jenkinson has talked about
this a lot as well and I asked him about
elders specifically because he's written
a book about that what's the role of
elders right now and he also then talked
about what is the role of artists so to
my mind it goes like this
you know elders are not people elders
are not personality types not at age
group an elder is by definition of verb
that means it has a sequence a kind of
cascading sequence of responsibilities
there the crew to individual people and
then pass them by not always the same
people all the time
you know comes and goes according to
their skillfulness and their willingness
to submit to life and so on like that
yeah although that's true but at the end
of the day you could say the the
fundamental Ellender function
is the same function as the function of
the artist
like this the artists responsibility is
to take their skillfulness develop it of
course learn like crazy and ultimately
the product of their work should
function prismatic Li not complementary
complementarily but prismatic Li by
which I mean that the culture which is
invisible to itself the daily comings
and goings of the culture basically like
the fish is water right we don't see it
something goes sideways we see it for a
little while and then we go back to not
seeing as quickly as we can but what the
art does is it takes the essentially
invisible culture the culture passes
through the art and the constituent
parts of the culture are refracted out
the other side that's the encounter with
the art the unbidden unsuspected
consequence of arousal or
discombobulation or you know whatever it
is and so the the principal
responsibility of the artist is to get
out of the way of the art so the culture
can pass through be refracted on the
other side with this caveat that the
artist has absolutely no obligation to
restore to reassure to soothe the
culture as a consequence of what the
artwork does okay they have to stand by
the consequence of the work and if
they're doing it very well indeed yeah
well you can think of examples of people
who've done that very thing and
unfortunately sometimes the culture will
turn turn them into politicians or
spokespeople for their generations and
they should resist all seduction to do
such a thing because that means they're
supposed to be complimentary of that
particular generation they stand for and
so forth so elders function in a similar
way I think elders responsibility is to
bear faithful witness to the current
circumstances the current regime
whatever the consequence of
truth-telling might be whatever calamity
ensues first things first the first
thing is
what's happening
and and the the benefit of their years
should be that they are able to find
ever more faithful language that bears
forward what's happening so that you
don't have to look past them
because they're no longer teaching
becoming practitioners of what they're
advocating
you just look to them and alas we live
in a time now where so many older people
are discredited for very understandable
and even legitimate reasons that it's
it's a deep challenging thing indeed to
try to decide what constitutes the
function of elder hood in a calamitous
time like ours is it really that guy
with his billions getting ready to send
you to Mars if you've got enough money
his dad who you wanna fall so that was
what really attracted me to Jordan
Peterson's work originally was this
sense of recapturing the mythopoetic and
especially young because Young was the
psychologist in the sort of early 20th
century mid twentieth century who went
more deeply into the unconscious than
just about anyone else and started
pulling out the ideas of archetypes and
so and I think there's an amazing quote
by Jordan Peterson where he said young
brought together the world of sort of
myth and story with science and
psychology and this was absolutely one
of the most crucial pieces of work that
was actually done in the 20th century we
embody a lot of information in our
action interaction has developed as a
consequence of imitating other people
and not only the people the people
around us but of course the people
around us imitated the people who came
before them and those people in potato
people who came before them and so on so
far back that it's as far back as you
can go and so you embody these patterns
of behavior that are extremely
informative that you don't understand
that are a consequence of collective
imitation across the centuries and so
then those patterns can become manifest
as figures of the imagination and those
figures of imagination are the
distillation zuv patterns of behavior
and so as the distillation zuv patterns
of behavior they have content and it's
not you that content it's you could even
think about it as content that's evolved
although it's culturally transmitted
this content that's evolved and so these
figures of the imagination can reveal
the structure of reality to you and
that's what happened with Jung and
that's what he described in the red book
and that was what permeated his
psychology a psychology that was Bey
stone the presupposition that the
fundamental archetypal structures of
religious belief were not pathological
not deceitful not protective in some
delusional sense against the fear of
death but quite the contrary the very
stories that enabled us to move forward
as confident human beings in the face of
chaos itself and it's conceivable
I think perhaps probable that nothing
more important conceptually happened in
the 20th century than that because it
was the first time post enlightenment
that ever approached menthe between the
intellect and the underlying religious
archetypal sub structure occurred you
have in the capacious intellect of Jung
and the same thing happened to some
degree with Piaget the religious domain
and the factual domain were brought back
together and the fact of use enduring
and increasing popularity and influence
I would say is it direct consequence of
that Jordan Peterson has now looked at
as a kind of why some people's are quite
reactionary figure in a quite a
traditionalist but actually that's
incredibly radical that kind of the
Jungian frame is an incredibly radical
frame to be bringing into academia and
bringing into even into kind of modern
culture when he first kind of arose it's
like wow he's taking Jung seriously he
was told by his colleagues at the
various institutions he was teaching at
not to go near Jung but that would be
career suicide don't go near and he kind
of went into it anyway
and that I think is a really that's what
I think made him such a kind of
archetypal figure himself
Jordan Peterson because he was bringing
this kind of archetypal force of the the
story of the culture and where that gets
integrated and where it's not integrated
is another question I think it's a
deeper question I'd love to unpack in
the future thinking about potentially
doing a film about the legacy of Jordan
Peterson's thought and that sort of
amazing trajectory that we saw over
though those kind of couple of years and
but that for me is really interesting
yeah I think really important when we're
talking about myth and story as a way to
make sense of the world and a way to
make sense of our experience is to
really draw on young and the just the
very idea that we have an unconscious as
individuals so that we are not aware of
everything that's going on with us in
fact we're not aware of most of what's
going on with us a lot of the time and
in that unconscious a part of ourselves
there are you know in Jung's theory and
this is really simplifying it but let's
say like encoded ways of being that are
very very old and that are you know
maybe drawn by experiences our ancestors
had many many many times so you know the
wise old woman or the wise old man and
the trickster and all these different
types of ways of being that we all can
embody at some point and can have access
to so there's that on the individual
level but it also spreads out to what
you can call the collective unconscious
and that's where this becomes especially
useful to look at you know what is
coming out of the collective unconscious
when we go through a major major shift
and a major crisis like we're seeing
right now and how do we how do we go in
there and trying to make sense of it and
a key thing to mention I think is that
part of the reason young is so difficult
to bring into academia is that young was
really sanitized by by young'uns after
he died
Peter Kings he's written a great book
called catafalque all about this and
about youngnam mystic and and how people
have misinterpreted him and this idea of
understanding the world in this very
let's say it's not the the way of
knowing of science because it's really
about symbolism and and nuance and
aesthetic and feeling and you know it's
so different to being able to sit down
and measure something but at the same
time we are able to at least map out in
a sense what myths can tell us and
probably the person who did that best or
one of the people who did it best was
joseph campbell who has a theory called
the monomyth which is the idea that all
of our mythic structures that we tell
all the stories we tell whether you're
in an inuit tried five hundred years ago
or you're in
you know at London in 20 20 weeks held a
sim the same structures over and over
because they are so deeply encoded in us
and it's really the story of our process
of discovery and change over time which
is also called the hero's journey hero's
journey and in fact Charlotte you can
who I spoke to you know she raised a
really interesting point about you know
is you know the hero's journey has been
recently criticized as being very male
focused and I've always been very
curious about this because I see that
trajectory play out in stories about
women as well so I kind of have issue
with that Charlotte you can mention this
very interesting thing that male
initiation and female initiation are
actually play out differently but they
actually still follow that trajectory of
we go from a place of somehow being
deluded or somehow being safe in our
little area or you know we're in the
Shire or we're on Tatooine if you look
Skywalker and then we step out into the
world into a different type of world
where we grow as a human being so it
might be that it's a call to adventure
or as Charlotte says and a lot of female
initiation stories you start at the top
and then you're right down and she calls
in the ashes all your everything is
stripped away which is the process we're
going through this stripping away of all
our pretenses are stripping away of the
nice dress you were wearing and then
you're sitting in the muck with a fire
but that process of coming back into the
earth is really regenerative so there's
such a richness to this whole area and
Charlotte has a really interesting take
on one myth in particular which is the
myth of psyche and I asked her a little
bit about why that myth is so important
right now and what I can tell us and and
the thing about the myth of psyche is
that I think I said in I talked about
this in the piece that you know her name
means butterfly and there's this image
of you know we are like a caterpillar
culture that's devouring everything
every green thing has been devoured and
at some point we have to go into the
cocoon and transform and in many ways
the self isolation is a kind of
cocooning in
we go and become a different kind of
human being I mean whether we're all
respond like that is a different matter
it remains to be seen but I feel it's a
really it's a very good metaphor and the
feeling of that one everything's
dissolving and question down is is part
of what happens in a cocoon when a
caterpillar becomes an amalgam yeah yeah
it's a nice image you mentioned just now
about that's all having us all going
through our own transformation in a
unique way we're all different in
outbreak in the piece we're just talking
about a thing you mentioned somewhere
that the female and the male initiatory
journey and myth is actually different
and that's an idea I'm really curious
about to want to hear a little bit more
about that and in what ways and of
course we probably know much more about
the male one because of the hero's
journey and just candle etc Chisholm
where I know a lot of my myth knowledge
from and so I'm really very curious
about is these different types of
initiation and how they might apply to
it right now well I think I think I mean
it was a broad generalization to say all
male on this so about going out and
doing hero's journey and because I don't
think they all are and some of them
contain moments of kissing ashes and
being confused and having to go down but
really in all of female myths that I've
read and fairy stories there is the
classic form is that you lose your shiny
it's like Cinderella ply down you start
at the palace and then you end up in
this in you know sitting by the fire by
the ashes with the mouse and with the
little creatures in in the kitchen and
this is called
this is what I call kitchen work they
won't start there but you know if you go
into the forest and encounter baba Yaga
in the in in the classic
Russian fairy tales she is a hard
taskmaster she's like Venus they are
tough because they know you have to be
tough and resourceful to live properly
on the planet they're not took men
they're not mean what they're teaching
you is that you can't be a princess but
we live in the princess culture I mean
well a lot girls doing I should say you
know and that is just it's not you can't
be a princess on the planet you can be
beautiful but you can't be a princess
and so this is what all the female must
say you need to go down you know stop
shopping at Primark it's not what it's
about it's interesting that you
mentioned the collective unconscious
because I think we've all had this sense
of feeling that sort of sense of the
collective consciousness much more than
ever before this sort of sense that
everyone is focused on the same thing
knowing that everyone is aware of the
same thing everyone is focused on the
same thing and that's sort of this sense
of initiation as well that the hero's
journey the monomyth is all about
initiation it's all about going from one
state to another and why it's so
relevant is that it Maps on to its the
process that we all individually go
through and then it's represented in me
it's represented in story and so that's
a really interesting frame to bring to
it as well this sort of sense of could
this crisis be a collective initiation
in some way I think it has to be I think
it's kind of like this is the sense that
I think a lot of people have had it's
like we can't waste this crisis and if
we do waste this crisis then we're gonna
just store up for another crisis that's
almost like to be bigger than this one
so another aspect of being in the
liminal or the space between worlds as
that calls it is that it's really a
trial it's an initiation and it's a
Charlotte you can actually said it's
really easy in myth to go into the
underworld it's really difficult to get
out of the underworld and that's what
really distinguishes a character and a
story and so Zac spoke spoke really well
about what it actually takes and what
what this process is of being in this
liminal space life life itself of knowin
out of your own doing will often create
situations
demand a profound change in your
identity right and again the loss of a
loved one spouse or a brother or sister
or something that will make you have to
change and so there's a dynamic to the
psyche where this is part of living that
we've become new people and so my
background was in developmental
psychology and philosophy of education
and the whole thing there Allah you know
Keegan and then others in Dawson and
Kirk Fischer is that actually we can we
can look at this actually works there
are ways that we are we are by just
growing up over time become new people
so that the mind can do this but for
many adults beyond the age of let's say
30 or so for various reasons it becomes
harder and harder to to to die to
yourself basically and to to create a
more responsive and adaptive way of
being it becomes harder to do that we
can go into that but that's not kind of
the point here so in this moment the
whole world is basically put into a
situation where again every unique
person contemplating their own unique
situation and unique death brings us to
a situation where kind of mass metanoia
right which is this a mass
transformation of psyche will occur and
then there's a question of will it
happen to us or will we try to gain
sovereignty and agency over the
transformation of self that's being
asked for them and this is the main
thing you can do as a support person for
someone in a process of transformation
right is to give them the scaffoldings
they need to be able to to choose to not
be subject to circumstance but to be
able to feel like they can be true to
their most important principles right
not like not protect them from pain but
actually put them in a position to be
able to know who they want to become
and to act from those principles which
means that no matter how bad it gets
you can keep your integrity and so it's
about moving the sense of self from the
kind of extrinsic motivation and
extrinsic reward system to a deep seat
of intrinsic motivation this is language
they came to me the other day the word
liminal comes from Lehman so threshold
Latin threshold in English I think the
etymology is is kind of disputed but
it's right at the edge of our door might
be where we have the fresh in or where
we clean our feet when I find that
fascinating it's like we are in this
very liminal space for work through the
threshold into this incredibly familiar
place into our homes I mean you you
think that kind of that kind of coming
home into the home is is a place to
start without reconnecting to ourselves
well this is gonna sound very ungenerous
but I'm not sure the lion's share of the
selves you just referred to is anything
that you'd really want to reconnect with
okay it's I mean it's an important
thought to consider right I mean if
you're just going to blame the Trump's
of the world for the way it is and the
Big Pharma and the you know all of that
and you basically absolve yourself of
any participation in it then what you
say stands we connect with ourselves but
we have to recognize that as citizens of
an alleged free country we aid in abet
the circumstances we lament so
desperately right and those selves you
were just referring to their principal
players and keeping this whole operation
going and if you have any doubt of that
look at the consequence of us keeping
those selves of ours to ourselves at
home the direct palpable consequence
just economically right so the world
could use less of ourselves it seems to
me and right now it may be enjoying
itself okay so as I said that sounds
ungenerous and I don't mean this in a
caustic or condemning fashion but it is
an invitation to consider this notion of
getting back or returning or reorienting
a reacquainting or all of that language
that habits are at the front of it is to
be suspected it's to be wondered about
it's like I don't know if you have this
where you are but certainly for the last
30 or 40 years people are using language
like rewilding which is absolutely
hilarious or getting back to the land
and anybody who had ever used that
phrase was never on the land to begin
with you see so there's no there's no
reacquainting to do it's learning it
getting familiar again
right so that's that's my my plea is to
not pick up where we left off to imagine
that the thing that was interrupted had
no business continuing and this this
virus this is a god
that's not overstating things this is a
God and the gods in the house and the
gods have in God's way as God tends to
do and our obligation is to be exercised
a kind of radical hospitality to this
anarchic presence
and to learn how to be undone by this
presence a really common theme was that
we are all of us right now together in
the wilderness somewhere you know
metaphorically we're out past the point
of no return in many ways and Zach Stein
said it really beautifully actually when
we're in the wilderness we have to carry
our temple with us so we have to I think
what he means by that is that the things
that matter most to us and the things
that will help us through and kind of
help us overcome are things that we have
to hold very dear and we have to keep
hold of them as we're in this really
liminal space and very practically for
me I think that translates to some of
those qualities that we can develop by
connecting with each other deeply and
authentically by increasing our
resilience by following the truth of our
experience and all of those core
qualities that so many wisdom traditions
and so many people have talked about for
years as being really key to cultivate
now it feels like more than ever it's
all coming to a fore and everything that
we might have been cultivating up until
now suddenly now is the time to use them
the adolescents who form their mature
adult identity under these conditions
are the ones who will lead the future
and so we need to be concerned about
ourselves of course as adults we need to
take care of ourselves as adults but we
need to take care of ourselves as adults
on behalf of this generation who is
coming of age during this so that's and
that's where the place of like the new
person emerging that's where that
becomes like most vibrant isn't that
that age group and so yes so that's a
little bit on that there's of course a
lot to say on that but I'm not trying to
say we all need to become this kind of
person you can transcend fear or we all
need to become this kind of person who
can like be there for others it's like
it's much more nuanced right now some
people need to go inside of themselves
and deal with their own before they
could ever go and out
people right um some right now some
people need to stop helping other people
so much so that they don't break down
and then become a burden on everyone
else right so there's a lot of dynamics
that are implying the key thing I'm
pointing to is and it's one I think it's
the first question in my essay you know
can we clarify the things that were most
committed to like the core of our
integrity as a person and if we know
that can we then understand what it
would mean to be that person under all
circumstances right and then we've found
a kind of compass and when it comes to
what are those core commitments and what
are the language that we use to describe
the things we would die for yeah that's
where we need to have discussions like
these that's where the dialogue goes
comes in where we talk about the deepest
parts of our lives that touch everything
right the issues of ultimate concern and
these are the conversations you fall
into with people in hospice work right
or in caregiving work or even in just
the state of fear of the ambient kind of
like skull grinning in on the banquette
right so yeah new people are coming and
it's this question of who who we will
who will choose to become essentially
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom gym a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon
[Music]